我知道你们不想弄这事
Look, I know you guys don't want to do this,
但我们没得选好吗
but we have no choice.
你们大可以唧唧歪歪  浪费时间
So, you can either bitch and whine
也可以通力合作  早点搞定
or we can just get it over with.
我负责唧唧
I got "whine."
我负责歪歪
I got the "b word."
我们与学校的合约中
Yeah, well, it's in our contract
注明了得为大学委员会服务
to serve on a university committee.
老实说  我也认同这件事
And frankly, this is one I believe in.
主题就是
Okay, here we go.
鼓励更多女性加入科学领域
Encouraging more women to pursue a career in the sciences.
拜托  我要有本事说服女人
Come on, if I was any good
去做我想她们做的事
at convincing women to do stuff,
那我20多岁时  就不用常自己在浴室"自乐"了
I wouldn't have spent so much of my 20s in the shower.
要我说的话
If you ask me,
搞这事根本只是浪费时间
this whole thing is a waste of our time.
帮助女性浪费时间吗
Helping women?
帮人就是浪费时间
Yeah, helping anyone.
人们应该自己照顾自己
People should take care of themselves.
比如像昨天
Oh, like yesterday,
你叫我载你去干洗店
when you made me drive you to the dry cleaners,
药店跟邮局那样吗
the pharmacy and the post office?
我又没说人们不能使用工具
I'm not saying people can't use tools.
连水獭想吃蛤蜊时都知道用石头敲开了
Even an otter picks up a rock when he wants a clam.
你觉得花时间
You don't think it's worthwhile
让更多女性加入科学行业不好吗
to try to get more women working in science.
我觉得你太有性别歧视了
I think that's incredibly sexist of you.
我相信在性别平等的社会
I believe in a gender-blind society
比如《星际迷航》中  各个种族
like in Star Trek, where women and men
信仰各异的男女都平等地一起共事
of all races and creeds work side by side as equals.
你是说那个先进到能发明出
You mean where they were advanced enough
能进行恒星际旅行的曲速引擎
to invent an interstellar warp drive,
却还是让一个黑人女性接太空电话的世界吗
but a black lady still answered the space phone?
我的浴室"自乐"时间有不少是跟
Oh, I did spend a lot of my shower time
乌乎拉通讯官度过的
with Lieutenant Uhura.
先不管霍华德的下流回忆
Howard's disturbing recollections aside,
我不喜欢被逼去做这些
I don't appreciate being forced to do
平庸的委员会工作
banal committee work.
是是是  太大材小用了
Yes, I know, you're too smart for this.
没错
Exactly.
就跟叫霹雳火
It's like asking the Human Torch
霹雳火是《神奇四侠》里的人物  能让全身变成火焰
来热你的冷冻玉米煎饼一样
to heat up your frozen burrito.
明白
Got it.
我想到了一个
All right, I'm thinking one way
避免在同行评审阶段遭受歧视的方法
to counter bias in the peer-review process,
就是报告都用中性名字递交
is for papers to be submitted under gender-neutral names.
比如S·史密斯
Like S. Smith
而不是沙曼莎·史密斯
instead of Samantha Smith.
专业领域的某些女性使用缩写名
I suppose there is a history of professional women
来避免先入为主的批判  的确行之有年了
using their initials, so as not to be pre-judged.
《哈利波特》作者  J.K.罗琳
Harry Potter's J.K. Rowling,
《星际迷航》编剧  D.C.丰塔纳
uh, Star Trek's D.C. Fontana.
范奈斯市的钢管舞女  DD杯·麦伦[巨乳]
Van Nuys pole-dancer D.D. Melons.
好啦  我们今天有帮到女性了
All right, I think we've really helped women today.
来打电动吧
Let's fire up the old Xbox.
你们俩  拜托别让历史重演
Guys, please don't make this a school project
小时候做报告  聪明孩子做全部
where I'm the smart kid doing all the work
其他懒鬼就在旁边看着
while the slackers sit back and watch.
我们才不是呢
No, we're not.
这次是聪明孩子负责做全部工作
This time you're the smart kid doing all the work
而更聪明的孩子在旁边看着
while the even smarter kids sit back and watch.
你觉得我也是更聪明的孩子吗
So, you think I'm one of the smarter kids?
不是  你只是我用来证明论点的工具
No, you're a tool I was using to make my point.
生活大爆炸 第六季  第十八集
我们的主题是"鼓励女性加入科学领域"
Guys, our topic is "Encouraging Women in Science."
你们俩不能玩少点性别歧视的游戏吗
Can you at least play a less sexist game?
这哪有歧视女性
How is it sexist?
我的角色能像男人一样把大战锤挥起来
My character wields a battle axe as well as any man.
更别说她有着超发达的乳腺
Not to mention she has mammary glands
足够喂养一家三十口
that could nurse a family of 30.
而且剩下来的量
And have enough milk left over
都够开冰激凌店用了
to open a Baskin Robbins.
母亲  战士公主  冰激凌加盟店老板
Mother, warrior-princess, franchise owner--
女性职场障碍全被打爆啊
I hear glass ceilings shattering all over town.
谢尔顿  你老说
Sheldon, you're always saying
你比我聪明无数倍
how much smarter you are than me.
那你能用五秒钟想出一个
Spend five seconds and come up with one idea
能让更多女性加入科学领域的方法吗
on how to get more women into science.
你的所有点子都仅限于学术界阶段的问题
All your ideas address the issue at a university level.
但那阶段已经太晚了
By then it's too late.
你应该设计一个扩展研究
You need to design an outreach program
把目标延伸到中学阶段的少女们
that targets girls at the middle school level
把她们导向追求学术
and sets them on an academic track
迈向硬科学的道路之上
towards the hard sciences.
还真是个好点子
That's actually good.
我怎么就没想到呢
Why didn't I think of that?
有些人是水獭  而有些人就只是石头
Some people are otters, some people are rocks.
有没有什么方法
I wonder if there's a way
可以先试验一下这点子呢
we could give the idea a trial run.
我可以试试打电话给我以前的中学
Maybe I could call my old middle school,
看我们能不能跟一些女学生聊聊
see if we can talk to some of the female students.
这不错啊  安排一下
That's great-- try to set up something
让我们三个去那里试试
for the three of us to go over there.
先等等吧
Oh, hold on.
虽然我对谈科学没有任何问题
While I'm comfortable speaking about science,
但我不确定能否勾起中学女孩的兴趣
I'm not sure I know how to spark the interest of schoolchildren.
我先上网搜搜吧
Better Google it.
你打算搜什么关键句
What exactly are you looking up?
"如何让12岁少女兴[性]奋"
"How do I get 12-year-old girls excited."
不要  快住手
No! No!
再次感谢你们让我参一脚"闺蜜之夜"
Thanks again for letting me crash "girls' night."
开什么玩笑
Are you kidding?
你带来上好的红酒  还给我们做芝士火锅
You brought fancy wine and made fondue.
比这小的好处我都"睡"过了
I've slept with guys for less.
开玩笑啦
It's a joke.
基于真实故事的玩笑
Based on real events.
总之  我希望可以
Anyway, I was hoping I could, uh,
向你们请教一下
pick your brains a little.
我周五要跟露西约会
I'm supposed to take Lucy out Friday
我需要一个超棒的初次约会
and I need a killer first date.
进化生物学说  女人容易被
Well, evolutionary biology says that women are attracted
临危不乱的男人所吸引
to a man who is steady in the face of danger,
所以我建议去危险的地方
so I recommend an unsafe environment.
去贫民区破旧的酒吧
Seedy bar on the wrong side of the tracks...
去疯人院附近野餐
picnic near a lunatic asylum...
去贫民窟品酒
a wine tasting on Skid Row.
露西有社交焦虑症
Eh, Lucy has some, uh, social anxiety issues.
或许我们可以从简单点的地方着手
Maybe we could start with something simpler.
你何不带她去迪士尼乐园
Why don't you take her to Disneyland?
你们可以玩室内过山车
You go on Space Mountain,
两人处于黑暗中  她紧紧抓住你
you're in the dark, she's holding onto you.
但千万要记住
Yeah, but you just have to remember,
那比你想象中还快结束
that ride is shorter than you think
终点前还会给你俩拍照
and they take a picture of you at the end,
所以记得在那之前就穿回衣服
so make sure you got your clothes back on.
开玩笑啦
It's a joke.
基于真实故事的玩笑
Based on real events.
迪士尼乐园  我不知道该不该去
Mm, Disneyland? I don't know.
人挤人  还有奇怪的角色玩偶人四处游走
With all the crowds and the weird characters walking around,
会让我有一种在印度的错觉
just reminds me too much of India.
我从来没去过迪士尼
I haven't been to Disneyland since I was a kid.
真应该找个周末去玩玩
We should definitely go one weekend.
周末人太多了
Weekends are too crowded.
那就不去上班  工作日时去
So, blow off work, go on a weekday.
翘班吗
Hooky?
我这辈子连课都没翘过
I've never played hooky in my life.
我妈说翘课的女生最后都会
My mom said that's how girls end up
沉迷于大麻和爵士乐
addicted to reefer and jazz music.
其实翘课的女生更有可能在酒店
It's more like how girls end up at a Best Western hotel
跟一个34岁的老头开房
with a 34-year-old guy named Luther.
也是玩笑吗
Joke?
我现在对此能一笑置之了
I can laugh about it now.
你们觉得怎么样
So, what do you say?
周五我们放下工作去迪士尼  好吗
This Friday we ditch work and go to Disneyland?
我赞成
I'm in.
我也赞成
Me, too.
打断一下
Excuse me,
你们不是要帮忙解决我的问题吗
I thought we were trying to solve my problem?
对哦  没错
Oh, yeah, right.
等下  你的问题是什么来着
Wait, what was your problem again?
我是一个无法跟女性正常交流的男人
I am a man who can't talk to women,
试图想出
trying to figure out
如何跟一个患有严重社交焦虑症
how to go on a romantic date with a girl
而无法跟人共处的女孩
who suffers from such crippling social anxiety
进行一次浪漫约会
she can't be around other people.
对哦  这还真有难度
Yeah, that's a toughie.
我们好好想想
Let's think.
我们是光去迪士尼  还是也去加州冒险乐园呢
We doing just Disney or California Adventure, too?
真是太好了  你的母校肯让我们
It's nice of your old school to let us try out
试验在一群女学生面前宣讲科学
our science talk on some female students.
他们其实挺开心的
Well, they're actually pretty excited.
我是他们最出名的毕业生
I'm their most famous alum.
如果不算那个奸杀妓女
If you don't count the serial killer
还吃掉她们的连环杀手的话
who ate all those prostitutes.
你的感觉一定很好吧
This must feel pretty good for you,
以宇航员的身份荣归母校
coming back to your alma mater as an astronaut.
那是  我上一次在这里时
Yeah, last time I was here,
我只是个骨瘦如柴的小阿宅
I was just a scrawny little nerd.
现在还是  不过是多了宇航员的身份
And now you're also an astronaut.
这里有我很多回忆
So many memories.
我经常在这些走廊里
I mean, how many times in these hallways
被人绊倒  被人打  还被吐口水
was I tripped, punched and spit on?
瞧  这是我以前的储物柜
Oh, look, here's my old locker.
虽然我是工程学的硕士
I have a masters in engineering
但我还是想不明白斯科特·坎宾斯基
and I still can't figure out how Scott Kapinski
是怎么把我和我的公文包一起塞进里面的
got me and my briefcase to fit in there.
干嘛
What?
没事
Nothing.
明智  我们可不想惹麻烦
Smart. We don't want any problems.
真不敢相信  我居然翘班去迪士尼
I can't believe I ditched work for Disneyland.
你怎么跟老板说的
What did you tell your boss?
我相当聪明  一步一步铺好哏
Oh, I was very clever, I did it in stages.
昨晚7点
At 7:00 last night,
我打去跟他说实验室的问题
I called about a problem at the lab
然后不经意地提到我要出去吃海鲜
and casually mentioned I was going out for seafood.
9点半
At 9:30,
我打去告诉他  我其中一个扇贝吃起来怪怪的
I called and told him that one of my scallops tasted weird.
11点半  我打过去说
At 11:30, I called and said
我吐得天昏地暗
I was throwing up like a fire hose.
12点45分
At 12:45,
我打过去  什么也不说就一直干呕
I called and made nothing but dry heaving sounds,
而现在我在去迪士尼的路上了
and now I'm going to Disneyland.
佩妮  你怎么说的
Penny, what did you say?
我在芝士蛋糕工厂上班
I work at the Cheesecake Factory,
说声再见就能甩头走人
I said "Bye."
我们先玩什么
So, what are we gonna do first?
我不知道你们俩想玩什么
I don't know about you guys,
但我要直奔一个地方
but I'm gonna make a beeline for the place
可以把你装扮成公主
that gives you a princess makeover.
听起来很好玩
Ooh, that sounds like fun.
你说笑呢  对吧
You're kidding, right?
我们不是要喝个大醉  然后去坐游乐设施吗
We're not just gonna get drunk and go on rides?
别这样  和我们一起玩嘛
Come on, do it with us.
好吧  随便吧
All right, whatever.
要怎么玩
How does it work?
你先选个公主
Okay, so, you pick your princess--
睡美人  白雪公主  灰姑娘
Sleeping Beauty, Snow White, Cinderella--
他们会帮你弄头发  化妆  弄全套
they give you hair, makeup, the works.
打扮成灰姑娘肯定很好玩
Guess it would be fun to be Cinderella.
-我也想当灰姑娘  -对啊
- Oh, I want to be Cinderella, too. - Yeah.
我们不能都当灰姑娘
We can't all be Cinderella.
那要怎么决定呢
Then how do we decide?
很简单
Well, it's simple.
这是我的主意
This was my idea.
开车的是我
I'm driving.
所以我是灰姑娘
I'm Cinderella.
你们两个小贱货要是有意见
You bitches got a problem with that,
我们现在就可以停车
we could stop the car right now.
不好意思  我约了女生在这里见面
Excuse me, I'm meeting a girl here.
这是我们的第一次约会
It's kind of our first date.
在图书馆吗
In a library?
我和她都有些不擅长社交
She and I are both a little awkward in social situations,
所以这里挺好的
so this seemed like a good idea.
也常有人说我挺怪的
People say I'm a little awkward, too.
我能加入你们吗
May I join you?
不行
No, you can't join us.
你赶紧走开
Just go-go climb back up
从哪儿来回哪儿去
whatever beanstalk you came down from.
你可以找到更好的
You can do better.
我们要在这里吃吗
Oh, we're eating here?
这是短信约会吗
We're having a texting date?
我喜欢
I love that.
你看短信的时候要记得
As you're reading, it will help to remember
我有超可爱的口音哦
I have an adorable accent.
好  大家准备好来个科学之旅了吗
Okay, who's ready for some science?
我也是
Me, too.
我是莱纳德·霍夫斯塔德博士
Okay, I am Dr. Leonard Hofstadter.
这是我的朋友库珀博士
I am here with my friends Dr. Cooper
和真正的宇航员霍华德·沃罗威茨
and real-life astronaut Howard Wolowitz,
我们会为你们展现
and we are going to show you girls
科学工作会有多酷
how cool a job in science can be.
你们问有多酷[冷]是吗
How cool, you ask?
大概有零下273度[绝对零度]
Well, how about negative 273 degrees,
热力学函数
因为那是熵达到其最小值时的温度
'cause that's the temperature at which entropy reaches its minimum value.
我刚才是开心地学到新知识了吗
Did I just learn something new and have fun doing it?
还有这种好事
What?
很好
All right!
现在有请理论物理学家
So now let's bring out theoretical physicist
谢尔顿·库珀博士
Dr. Sheldon Cooper.
你们好  女孩子们
Hello, female children.
请允许我用一个
Allow me to inspire you
伟大的女性科学家的故事来激励你们
with a story about a great female scientist.
在波兰出生  在法国接受教育的
Polish-born, French-educated
居里夫人
Madame Curie.
她是放射线的发现人之一
Codiscoverer of radioactivity,
是科学界的英雄
she was a hero of science...
直到她的头发掉光
until her hair fell out;
吐血和大便带血
her vomit and stool became filled with blood...
她被自己的发现毒死了
and she was poisoned to death by her own discovery.
只要勤奋努力
With a little hard work,
你们一定都能获得她的成果
I see no reason why that can't happen to any of you.
结束了没  我们能走了吗
Are we done? Can we go?
重要的是
The thing to remember is
你们也可以去外太空
you can go to outer space, too.
瞧瞧我
I mean, look at me.
我以前就是这个学校的学生
I went to this very school.
你们坐着的其中一张课桌
Those desks you're sitting in,
我曾经被人用强力胶粘在上面过
I was once superglued to one of them.
你去月球了吗
Did you go to the moon?
没有  但我确实去了
No, but I did go to
国际太空站
the International Space Station.
你驾驶火箭了吗
Did you fly the rocket?
没有
No,
但我确实乘坐了火箭
but I was in the rocket.
我没有
I didn't actually...
所以你就是飞而已  和我叔叔很像
So you just flew around? That's kind of like my uncle.
他是个空乘员
He's a flight attendant.
不
No...
我是美国的英雄
I'm an American hero.
而你叔叔只会让人抓狂
Your uncle brings people nuts, okay?
我们学到了很多是吧
Boy, we are learning a lot here, huh?
谢谢你  霍华德宇航员
Thank you, Astronaut Howard.
我是一名实验物理学家
Um, I am what's called an experimental physicist,
我的工作特别好玩  因为我能测试证明理论
which is super-fun, because I get to test theories
工作还能跟激光打交道
and work with lasers.
请讲
Yes?
你是怎么决定当个科学家的
How did you decide to become a scientist?
这问题提得好
Uh, excellent question.
我从小就喜欢科学
Um, I suppose I've always been into science, you know...
我的妈妈爸爸都是科学家
My mother and father are scientists,
所以他们一直引导我走上这条路
so I was kind of led in that direction.
我是被逼的  这种形容更恰当
Eh, pushed might be a better way to describe it.
说句实话
To be honest with you guys,
我在你们这么大的时候
when I was your age,
我想当的是说唱明星
I wanted to be a rap star.
像史诺普·道格一样
Like Snoop Dogg,
史诺普·道格  美国说唱歌手
犯有私藏枪支和大麻罪
但是对警方更为尊重
but with a healthy respect for the police.
没关系  你们笑吧
Yeah, no, sure, you laugh.
我妈也笑了
Just like my mother did.
* 我对她坦诚相告 *
* After I confided, *
* 她对我责备嘲笑 *
* I was derided and chided, *
* 我们俩碰撞引爆 *
* my moms and I collided. *
* 她说我路走歪掉 *
* She said my dreams were misguided. *
随便即兴说唱两句
That's just a little freestyle.
我爸爸是印度的妇科医生
My dad's a gynecologist in India,
如果你去了印度  需要检查一下
so if you're over there and need a check-up,
子宫cervix与服务service音似
原意是"为你效劳"
用他的话来说  他愿意"检查你的子宫"
as he likes to say, he's "at your cervix."
太坏了
That's terrible.
penitentiary是监狱  但pun-itentiary则是双关语监狱
你爸爸该被送进"双关"监狱
Your dad should be sent to the pun-itentiary.
真是个合适的[双关]惩罚
That's a fitting pun-ishment.
我还不知道你的工作呢
I still don't know what you do for a living.
网页设计
Web design.
有我可能看过的网页吗
Anything I might have seen?
我不知道
I don't know.
你浏览过色情网站吗
You ever look at porn web sites?
从来没有
No, never.
那是什么
What is porn?
不好意思  自动纠错功能
Sorry. Autocorrect.
我本来打的是
That was supposed to say
"舞会网站"
"Prom Web sites."
真有趣  我喜欢舞会
Ooh, fun. I love prom.
气氛浪漫  锦衣华服
The romance, the gowns,
简直就像童话成真了
it's like a fairy tale come to life.
不好意思  自动纠错功能
Sorry. Autocorrect.
我本来打的是
That was supposed to say,
"我喜欢运动"
"I like sports."
我从来都不想拉大提琴
I never wanted to play the cello.
拉大提琴怎么泡得到女孩啊
How do you meet girls playing the cello?
"你想来我家
"Hey, you want to come over to my house
听我演奏一种乐器吗
and listen to me play an instrument
那听起来像大黄蜂自杀的声音哦"
that sounds like a suicidal bumblebee?"
赶紧去拉响火警报警器
Quick, pull the fire alarm.
好让咱们趁机溜走
Let's get out of here.
各位  再次问好
Uh, hello again.
我不知道是不是所有的女人
Um, yeah, I don't know if women in general
都被人主动劝阻过
have been actively discouraged
不要追求科学
from pursuing the sciences,
但很显然  今天你们这些女孩都被劝阻了
but it's clear you young women here, today, have been.
我听着我同事们废话连篇浪费你们的时间
While I was listening to my colleagues waste your time,
我突然想到  如果让真实的科学女强人
it occurred to me that it might be much more meaningful
为你们讲述女人投身科学的事迹
to hear about women in science
这样也许更有意义
from actual women in science,
我碰巧认识两位科学女强人
and, uh, I happen to know two brilliant examples
她们同意现在和你们进行电话交流
who have agreed to speak to you on the phone right now.
罗斯滕科夫斯基博士
Uh, Dr. Rostenkowski,
福勒博士  你们在吗
Dr. Fowler, are you there?
我们在
We're here.
感谢两位在百忙之中抽出宝贵的时间
Thank you for taking time out of your very busy schedule
来启发年轻的女孩子们
to enlighten these young women.
乐意之至
It's our pleasure.
白雪公主
我是福勒博士  神经科学家
I'm Dr. Fowler, and I'm a neuroscientist.
我是罗森考斯基·沃罗维茨博士
And I'm Dr. Rostenkowski Wolowitz,
灰姑娘
微生物学家
and I'm a microbiologist.
科学世界需要更多女性
The world of science needs more women,
但女孩们从小就被教导成
but from a young age, we girls are encouraged to care
更在乎自己的外貌
more about the way we look
而不是头脑的力量
than about the power of our minds.
是的
That's true.
你们每一个人都有能力
Every one of you has the capacity
成为自己想当的人
to be anything you want to be.
睡美人
但想当灰姑娘就不行
Unless you want to be Cinderella.
来单挑啊
Come at me.
看看谁厉害
See what happens.
今天真的很好玩
This was really fun.
我的手机要没电了  我就用说的吧
My battery's dying, so I'm just gonna talk.
谢谢今天你约我出来
Thanks for today.
我一直试着做更多让我害怕的事情
I've been trying to do more things that scare me,
来这和你约会绝对是其中之一
and coming here was definitely one of them.
但今天真挺不错的
But it was also really nice.
所以  谢谢
So thanks, and, um,
我打算走了
I'm gonna go.
也许我在离开前
Maybe I could do one more scary thing
能再做一件可怕的事  和你吻别
before I go and give you a kiss good-bye?
如果你同意的话
You know, if that's okay.
好吧  好吧
Okay. Okay.
恐慌症发作  下次吧
Panic attack! Maybe next time.
我就把这算做前戏了
I'm counting that as foreplay.
妮妮  我回家了
Bernie, I'm home.
你今天玩的开心吗
You have fun today?
开心  而且我为你准备了惊喜
Yes, and I have a surprise for you.
一定要是灰姑娘  一定要是灰姑娘
Please be Cinderella. Please be Cinderella.
你好啊  白马王子
Well, hello, Prince Charming.
小姐
Milady.
你今天...  什么情况
Hey, how was your... what?
我能解释
I can explain.
我和姑娘们翘班
I played hooky with the girls,
一起去了迪士尼乐园  然后...
then we all went to Disneyland and got...
你在干什么呢
What are you doing?
迪士尼乐园嘛  继续说  我听着呢
Disneyland. Go on, I'm listening.
谢尔顿  白雪公主只需要
Sheldon, all Snow White needs
轻轻一吻就能醒来哦
is one little kiss to wake up.
你说第一次时我就听见了
Heard you the first time.